http://youtu.be/_DgexVhva9E
http://youtu.be/_DgexVhva9E
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Well, Professor Yerraballi, what are
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: này thầy Yerraballi,
we gonna learn today?
chúng ta sẽ học gì hôm nay?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Well, we're gonna try something a little
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:  à, ta sẽ thử vài thứ
challenging.
khó nhằn 1 chút.
But we'll try and keep things simple.
Nhưng tôi sẽ cố gắng giải thích mọi thứ 1 cách đơn giản.
We're gonna learn the basics of electrical circuits in
Ta sẽ tóm lược những thứ cơ bản
an abbreviated session.
về mạch điện.
So let's hope we can get you to understand the basics and apply them
Ta nên hiểu về những thứ căn bản và áp dụng chúng
as it is relevant in the context of embedded systems.
vào hệ thống nhúng khi cần.
Let's look at the foundations that govern electrical circuits.
Hãy học những nền tảng tạo nên mạch điện.
Electric circuits are made up of basic elements, what we call as passive
Mạch điện được tạo từ những thành phần cơ bản, gồm phần bị động
elements and active elements.
và phần chủ động.
But before we get to those elements, we want to define some terms.
Nhưng trước khi học tới những phần đó, ta cần định nghĩa vài thuật ngữ.
So the first term that I'm going to look at is current.
Đầu tiên là dòng điện.
Current is the flow of charge.
Dòng điện là dòng chuyển dời có hướng của các hạt mang điện.
And when we say charge, we're looking at a positive or negative charge.
có thể là điện tích dương hay âm.
In our case, we're going to look at electrons as a unit of charge.
Trong trường hợp này, ta xem electron là đơn vị điện tích.
So the units for current are, because it's a flow of electrons, we're going
Với dòng điện, vì là dòng của eletron, ta sẽ dùng
to look at it as coulombs per second.
đơn vị là coulomb trên giây.
In other words, it's a rate of flow of charge, and charge, the units for
Nói cách khác, nó đo dòng chảy của hạt mang điện, mà hạt mang điện có đơn vị là
charge is coulombs, so it's coulombs per second.
coulombs, cho nên đơn vị là coulombs trên giây.
So rather than say coulombs per second, we use a term called amperes
Nhưng thay vì xài đơn vị là coulomb trên giây, ta có đơn vị khác là Ampere
to represent current.
để đại diện cho dòng điện.
So the idea, then, is current flows, current is the flow of electrons, or
Tóm lại, dòng điện là dòng chuyển dời có hướng của các hạt mang điện, có thể là electron,
the flow of charge.
hoặc hạt mang điện khác.
And the units for current are amperes.
Có đơn vị là Ampere.
Current has a direction, as we will see, and so when we talk about
Dòng điện thì có hướng, như ta sẽ thấy, khi nói về dòng điện
current, we're always talking about the flow of current, where it makes
là dòng chuyển dời có hướng của các hạt mang điện, cho nên
sense to talk about the direction in which current flows.
quan trọng dòng điện đang theo hướng nào.
So through a conductor, we say that current flows in some direction.
Xuyên qua vật dẫn, ta sẽ thấy dòng điện có vài hướng.
So the second term we're gonna look at is voltage.
Cho nên thuật ngữ kế tiếp ta nói về điện áp.
Voltage is what we call as electromotive force.
Điện áp là cái ta gọi lực điện động.
Electromotive force are sometimes called potential difference.
Lực điện động hay là hiệu điện thế
And the idea of voltage is always, we talk of voltage as a difference in
Cho nên điện áp, là hiệu điện thế
potential between two points.
giữa 2 điểm.
So when I say, for example, points a and b, we refer to the voltage as Vab
Cho nên khi tôi nói, ví dụ, 2 điểm a và b, ta có điện áp Vab,
as a potential difference between points a and b.
tức là hiệu điện thế giữa 2 điểm a và b.
Now, the definition of voltage is it's the amount of energy, so amount of
Định nghĩa của điện áp là lượng năng lượng cần để
energy needed to move one unit of charge, in this case a unit of charge
dời 1 điện tích, đơn vị của điện tích là coulomb,
is a coulomb, from a to b,
từ điểm a tới b,
from one point to another point. One volt will deliver one joule of energy per coulomb of charge that passes through it.
từ điểm này tới điểm khác. 1 Volt sẽ phóng thích 1 lượng năng lượng 1 Joule trên mỗi Coulomb của hạt mang điện đi qua nó.
So that is the voltage.
Đó là điện áp.
So voltage, then, has the units of joules, which is the unit for energy
Vậy điện áp có đơn vị là Joules, đơn vị của năng lượng
per coulomb.
trên Coulomb.
Again, we have a short for this.
Lần nữa, ta có đơn vị khác gọn hơn.
We simply call these volts.
là Volt.
So the units for current are amperes, and the unit for voltage is volts.
Đơn vị của dòng điện là Ampere, của điện áp là Volt.
So Ohm's law gives us a relationship between voltage and current, the two
Định luật Ohm cho chúng ta mối quan hệ của điện áp và dòng điện.
terms that we just introduced.
2 khái niệm mới vừa giới thiệu.
So what Ohm's law says is that the current that flows through a
Định luật Ohm nói rằng dòng điện chạy qua vật dẫn
conductor, and here I'm going to represent this conductor like this,
tôi vẽ vật dẫn như thế này,
the current that flows through a conductor from its positive side to
chạy qua vật dẫn từ phần dương sang phần âm,
the negative side, we call those a and b, which are positive and negative.
ta gọi 2 điểm này là a và b, có dấu dương và âm.
So Vab is a voltage across these two points, and it's saying that the
Vab là điện áp giữa 2 điểm, và
current and the voltage are related by a rule that says V equals I times R.
dòng điện và điện áp có mối quan hệ bằng 1 quy luật là V = I*R.
Where R is the resistance of the conductor.
với R là điện trở của vật dẫn.
So we can write it in various ways, and so for example, I can say R equals
Ta có thể biểu diễn nhiều cách khác nhau, ví dụ,
V by I, or I can say I equals V over R. All these are different forms of
R=V/I, hay I=V/R.
Ohm's law where R is given, R is the resistance, and the unit for
Với R là điện trở, đơn vị của điện trở R là
resistance R ohms.
Ohm.
So we have Ohm's law, which is giving us the relationship between these two,
Vậy ta có định luật Ohm, cho ta mới quan hệ giữa các khái niệm này,
but what we also say is that when current flows, we say we're talking
nhưng khi nói về dòng điện, ta đang nói về
about the flow of current.
dòng các hạt mang điện.
And we say the power dissipated, if you will, through this resistance is
Và công suất tiêu tán qua điện trở là
given by the voltage times V times I. And the units for power are watts.
V*I. Đơn vị của công suất là Watt.
And the interesting thing is that we can actually derive this as being
Và điều thú vị là nó bằng với
joules per second.
Joule trên giây.
And this is simply because the unit for voltage is joules per coulomb, and
Đơn giản bởi vì đơn vị của điện áp là Jould trên Coulomb, và
the units for current are coulombs per second.
đơn vị của dòng điện là Coulomb trên giây.
So the units for power is joules per second, which is also called watts.
Nên đơn vị của công suất là Joule trên giây, cũng là Watt,